创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning there was darkness,
随着一声爆炸
and then, bang--
诞生了无尽膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence
时间 空间和物质
of time, space and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在揭秘这个诡异
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
震撼 神秘莫测的
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets
地方 - 我们所谓的《宇宙》
of a place we call "The Universe."
在《星球大战》的宇宙间 死星
In the "Star Wars" universe, the Death Star
是终极大规模杀伤性武器
is the ultimate weapon of mass destruction,
能够消灭整个行星
able to annihilate entire planets.
在实际的宇宙间
In the actual universe,
空中充满了活生生的死亡之星
the sky is filled with real-life death stars.
它们可以视为定时炸弹
They can be thought of as sort of a time bomb.
有些是靠近我们星球的威胁
Some are dangerously close to our planet.
一旦辐射抵达我们这里 地球上的生命将可能遭遇严重的打击
Earth's life might take a bad hit when that radiation reaches us.
那就是地球撞上了它的枪口
And one has the Earth in its crosshairs.
它让人震惊不已
It was almost a shock.
我第一次看到时简直不敢相信
I didn't believe it when I first saw it.
它们就是死亡之星
They are the death stars,
它们把宇宙变成了异常险恶的地方
and they make the universe a very dangerous place.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：HDC字幕组 调校：晴天 招募Q号: 76846146
历史频道 - 宇宙 第4季第1集 死星
The History Channel - The Universe s04e01 Death Stars
距离地球数千光年之外
Thousands of light-years from the Earth,
一颗超大质量恒星正在启动自我毁灭的按钮
a supermassive star is preparing to hit the self-destruct button.
宇宙间每天都有恒星爆发
Stars explode every day in the universe,
不过这一个与众不同
but this one is different.
它蛰伏在人马座 -
It lurks in the constellation Sagittarius,
黄道十二星座里的神话射手
the mythological archer of the celestial zodiac.
此星叫做WR 104
The star is called WR 104,
其破坏力可能针对我们
and its destructive force could be targeting us
正瞄准着我们这颗脆弱的蓝色星球
and taking aim at our fragile blue planet
其致命的辐射将点燃我们的臭氧保护层
with enough deadly radiation to ignite our protective ozone layer.
这将激起剧烈的气候变化
This would incite drastic climate change,
造成许多动植物种的灭绝
cause the extinction of many plant and animal species,
甚至人类的消亡
and potentially the demise of mankind.
WR 104只是宇宙间数以百万计的大死亡之星中的一个
WR 104 is just one of millions of massive death stars in the universe.
这些凶险的天体是暮年巨星
These savage celestial bodies are aging giants,
正安排着自我爆发以进入星际来世
preparing to blast themselves into a stellar afterlife.
此时 星体的表层
At that point, the outer layers of the star
已无任何东西留下来支撑它们抵抗重力
have nothing left to support them against gravity.
这样它们突然向内塌落
So they suddenly fall inwards.
它们最后一口气可以引发已知宇宙间最大的爆发
Their last breath can ignite the biggest explosion in the known universe,
伽玛射线爆
a gamma ray burst,
爆发远超过我们的太阳整个100亿年生命中
a blast far exceeding the energy output of our own Sun
所输出的能量
over its entire 10-billion-year life.
要是其击中地球 我们所知的生命将不复存在
If one were to target the Earth, life as we know it could cease to exist.
这就是WR 104可能发生的情况
This is what could happen with WR 104,
正使其成为现实生活的死星
making it a real-life death star.
在影片《星球大战》中
In the film "Star Wars,"
死星是邪恶势力的终极武器
the Death Star is the dark side's ultimate weapon.
掠夺星纯属科幻
The predatory star is pure science fiction,
但是现实中要更为恐怖
but the reality is much scarier.
现实生活中的死星是恒星爆发
A death star in real life is a star that blows up
以致命的辐射冲击附近所有的行星
and blasts any nearby planets with deadly radiation.
你知道 那就是真正的死星
You know, that's a real death star.
WR 104是所谓的沃尔夫-拉叶星
WR 104 is what's known as a Wolf-Rayet star.
它们是宇宙间最大的恒星
They are the largest stars in the universe,
比我们太阳大30倍的巨兽
hulking beasts 30 times bigger than our own Sun,
个个都在倒数计时至世界末日
each of them counting down to Armageddon.
法国天文学家查尔斯 沃尔夫和乔治 拉叶在1867年发现
Discovered by French astronomers Charles Wolf and Georges Rayet in 1867,
沃尔夫-拉叶星是宇宙中的歹徒
Wolf-Rayet stars are the outlaws of the universe.
恒星的生存有其信条 -
Stars live by the credo,
生命短暂者 英年早逝 留下漂亮的躯壳
"Live fast, die young, leave a good-looking corpse."
它们越大 生命就越短
And the bigger they are, the faster they live,
生命越短 死亡就越暴戾
and the faster they live, the more violent their end.
它们通过极快地燃烧自己的核燃料
They burn through their nuclear fuel extremely quickly
耗尽自己所有的一切
and exhaust everything that they have,
因此它们生命不会很长
and so consequently they don't live very long,
至多也就几千万年而已
maybe a few tens of millions of years at most.
它们很容易找到 因为它们是星际王国中
And they're easy to find, because they're the real T. rexes
真正的霸王龙
of the stellar kingdom.
它们强大无比
They're immensely powerful.
在2000年 澳洲天文学家彼得 塔特希尔
In the year 2000, Australian astronomer Peter Tuthill
开始研究沃尔夫-拉叶星104 距离地球约8000光年
began studying Wolf-Rayet 104, some 8,000 light-years from Earth.
这颗巨星的凶险与众不同
This giant was ominously different from the others.
塔特希尔的团队立马就注意到了其周围巨大的尘埃云
Tuthill's team immediately noticed an immense dust cloud around it,
比我们整个太阳系大了20倍
20 times larger than our entire solar system.
我们知道沃尔夫-拉叶星104周围存在着尘埃
We knew there was dust around WoIf-Rayet 104,
让人大惑不解
and that was a puzzle,
因为那就好象是发现了地狱里的雪花一样
because it's a bit like finding a snowflake in hell.
那是个谜团
There was a mystery there,
我们试图解决这个谜团
and we wanted to try and solve that mystery.
在过去的六年中 塔特希尔利用夏威夷的
Over the course of six years, Tuthill used an infrared camera
凯克天文台的红外摄像机
at the Keck Observatory in Hawaii
通过多重曝光创建了一个复合图像
to create a composited image from multiple exposures.
它产生了惊人的延时排列
It yielded an amazing time-lapse sequence.
104星正在形成一个怪异的螺旋尘埃柱
104 was producing an exotic spiraling plume of dust.
它让人震惊不已
It was almost a shock.
我第一次看到时简直不敢相信
I didn't believe it when I first saw it.
我想 恒星看上去不会是螺旋的
I thought, stars don't look like spirals.
我看过的书中从未有过螺旋的
There's no spiral I've ever seen in a book.
我们于是手忙脚乱起来
We then had a mad scramble.
我们必须努力了解
We had to try and understand
恒星怎么会产生这个漂亮的尾巴的
how a star can produce this elegant tail.
塔特希尔发现这个怪异的尘埃螺旋的关键
Tuthill discovered that the key to this strange dust spiral
就在于事实上WR 104不是孤立的
was the fact that WR 104 wasn't alone.
它与一颗较小的恒星一起被锁定在
It's locked in orbit with a smaller star
所谓的双星系的轨道上
in what's known as a binary system.
双星喷射出的大量的带电粒子叫做星风
Both stars eject masses of charged particles called stellar winds.
这些风在宇宙中并不罕见
These winds aren't uncommon in the universe.
我们太阳产生的太阳风吹过了外行星
Our own Sun creates a solar wind that extends beyond the outer planets.
所不同的是 双星系里
The difference is that, in a binary system,
星风来自两颗恒星的碰撞
when winds from the two stars collide,
气体压缩了 烟尘就产生了
gases are compressed, and dust and soot are created.
但是究竟是什么引起这种尘埃形成了这样奇特的螺旋的呢？
But what causes this dust to form into such an exotic spiral?
草坪洒水器倒是个不错的比喻
So it turns out that a lawn sprinkler makes a great analogy
来阐述发生在这些碰撞风的双星系里的物理学
to illustrate the physics that's occurring in these colliding-wind binary systems.
我们改造了这个洒水器
We've modified this sprinkler
使其龙头只能射出一股水流
so that it only shoots one jet out of the spigot.
单股水流代表源源不断的尘埃粒子
The single water jet represents the constant flow of dust particles
由碰撞星风产生出来
being created by the colliding stellar winds.
但是因为WR 104星系里的两颗恒星
But because the two stars in WR 104's system
运行在相互缠绕的轨道上
are in constant orbit around each other,
对尘埃流附加了圆周运动
it adds a circular motion to the stream of dust.
你的第一直觉就是水流在进行圆周运动
Your first intuition is that the water is moving in a circular motion.
但事实上 草坪洒水器
But in actual fact, the lawn sprinkler
其实射出的是一条直线
is really shooting a jet in a straight line.
水滴
The water droplets,
即使它们是从洒水器里直线射出
even though they're moving in a straight line away from the spigot,
它们也产生了一个弧线
they create an arc,
弧线缠绕在了旋转的螺旋里了
and that arc wrapped into a spiral with the rotation.
螺旋甚至产生了更多的问题
The spiral spawned even more questions.
最头痛的是
The most troubling--
WR 104究竟会成为何种死星呢？
exactly what kind of death star could WR 104 become?
沃尔夫-拉叶星可以被视为是定时炸弹
Wolf-Rayet stars can be thought of as sort of a time bomb,
因为它们个头庞大 所以它们无法生存很久
because they're so massive that they can't live for very long,
一旦它们燃尽它们所有的核燃料
and once they've burned up all of their nuclear fuel,
就无任何东西留下以支持星体抵抗重力无情的引力
there's nothing left to support the star against the relentless pull of gravity.
到那时 星核塌缩
And at that point the core of the star collapses,
表层随之塌落
and the outer layers fall in on top of it
在巨大的爆炸中向外弹出
and bounce outward in a tremendous explosion.
这个爆炸就是超新星 巨大的辐射爆发
The explosion is a supernova, an immense burst of radiation
短暂照亮整个星系
that briefly outshines an entire galaxy.
沃尔夫-拉叶星104肯定会成为超新星的
Wolf-Rayet 104 will definitely go supernova
在未来的几十万年里的某个时间
sometime in the next few hundred thousand years.
相距8000光年
At 8,000 light-years away,
爆炸本身不会对地球构成威胁
the explosion itself poses no threat to the Earth.
但是不排除该超新星会引发
But there's a chance the supernova will trigger
宇宙间最狂暴的事件 -
the most violent event in the universe,
伽玛射线暴
a gamma ray burst.
这些大质量死星中比例不大的
In a small percentage of these massive death stars,
伽玛射线暴
a gamma ray burst is triggered
是垂死之星挤压转变成黑洞所引发的
by the crushing transformation of a dying star into a black hole.
在恒星塌缩的过程中 它会产生一个巨大的电场
As a star collapses, it produces a massive electric field.
瞬间 电场产生的能量
And in an instant, the energy from this electric field
转换成了物质和反物质粒子
is turned into matter and antimatter particles,
于是由于相互之间的碰撞
which then collide with each other
产生了巨大的能量脉冲
and produce a huge pulse of energy.
它们是电磁频谱中最强大的能量束
They are the most powerful energy beams in the electromagnetic spectrum,
杀伤力胜过微波 红外能 甚至X射线
more lethal than microwaves, infrared energy, and even X-rays.
人类已经学会利用致命的伽玛射线
Humans have learned to harness deadly gamma rays
派上有益的用途 诸如食品辐照
for useful purposes, such as food irradiation.
通过利用伽玛射线
By using gamma rays,
食品加工可以消除微生物 细菌
food processors can eliminate microorganisms, bacteria,
病毒以及虫类
viruses, and insects.
但是伽玛射线的施加量
But the amount of gamma radiation applied
是星际伽玛射线暴所释放能量的极微小的一丁点
is an extremely tiny fraction of the energy released in a stellar gamma ray burst.
伽玛射线暴所产生的巨大辐射
Gamma ray bursts produce so much radiation
相当于要是我们在地球上创造一个伽玛射线暴
that if we were to create a gamma ray burst on Earth,
就会像是无数核弹同时引爆
it would be like a huge number of nuclear bombs going off.
会摧毁地球上的生命
It would be devastating for life on Earth.
对于人类来说
For the human race,
有关伽玛射线暴最关键的信息
the most critical piece of information about gamma ray bursts
就是它射击的方向
is the direction of fire.
在塌缩的那一刻
At the moment of collapse,
恒星变成致密 扁平的圆盘
the star becomes a dense, flattened disk,
旋转轴的两极
and the rotational axis poles
是其密集星际物质释放的唯一出路
are its only openings free of dense star matter.
你会看到沿着两极的两个对应的排泄区
You get two relatively evacuated regions along the poles.
物质可以沿着那两个方向喷出
And it's along those directions that material can be ejected,
因为遇到的阻力相对较小
because it encounters relatively little resistance.
这个酸奶瓶提供了一个很好的比喻
So this container of yogurt provides a nice analogy
来说明伽玛射线暴里所发生的情况
for what happens in a gamma ray burst.
我将投下这只酸奶瓶
I'm going to drop the container of yogurt,
因为瓶子有侧边
and because of the sides of the container,
酸奶是不能够沿着这些方向出来
yogurt is not going to be able to go out along those directions.
但是瓶子的顶部是敞开的
But the top of the container is open,
因此酸奶会沿着顶部喷出来
so yogurt is going to squirt out along the top.
来看看发生的情况
Watch what happens.
酸奶基本上是直接往上喷出来的
So the yogurt went squirting basically straight up.
它不能从旁边出来
It couldn't go out the sides,
因为被奶瓶的侧边给挡住了
because it was blocked by the sides of the yogurt container.
这就是对伽玛射线暴里所发生情况的很好的比喻
And that's a nice analogy for what happens in a gamma ray burst.
人类最为关切的
The greatest concern for humans
伽玛射线暴所对准的方向
is the direction that the gamma ray burst is firing.
如果塌缩恒星的轴指向我们的方向
If the axis of the collapsing star is pointing in our direction,
我们就会陷入严重的险境
we could be in serious trouble.
彼得 塔特希尔小组在研究WR104的
When Peter Tuthill's team studied the plane of orbit
尘埃柱的轨道平面时 得到了惊人的认识
of WR 104's dust plume, they came to a shocking realization.
这个螺旋解开这大量秘密的关键
This spiral was the key that unlocked a lot of these secrets.
事情开始变得有点吓人的地方
And where things start to get a little scary
就在于这个星系 乍看之下 几乎是正面迎对
is that this system, at first blush, appears to be almost face-on.
我们正对着轴心
We're looking right down the axis at the heart.
它看上去就像是一只盘子 餐盘
It's like looking at a plate, a dinner plate.
如果你拿起那个平面 把它跟视线有点倾斜
If you take that plane, and you tilt it to the line of sight,
看上去就是倾斜的
it looks inclined.
你就再也看不到一个圆圆的餐盘了
You're no longer looking at a circular dinner plate.
进一步研究表明尘埃柱的旋转轴
Further examination suggests the rotational axis of the dust plume
似乎与沃尔夫-拉叶星本身的旋转轴相吻合
appears to match the rotational axis of the Wolf-Rayet star itself,
这意味着地球直接就在枪口上
meaning the Earth is staring directly down the barrel of a gun.
也就是说 要是这颗恒星爆发成为伽玛射线暴时
That means that if this star becomes a gamma ray burst when it blows up,
两股射流之一会朝我们而来
one of the two jets will be pointing toward us.
沃尔夫-拉叶星104漂亮的螺旋
The beautiful spiral of Wolf-Rayet 104
突然成了厄运的使者
is suddenly a messenger of doom.
距离地球约8000光年
Some 8,000 light-years from Earth,
两颗恒星被锁定在一个引力舞蹈中
two stars are locked in a gravitational dance,
其星风在优美的螺旋中喷射出巨大的尘埃云
their stellar winds ejecting a vast cloud of dust in a graceful spiral.
但是这对星际伙伴远不止光有一条漂亮的尾巴
But there's more to this star couple than just a beautiful tail.
两者中较大者 沃尔夫-拉叶104星
The larger of the two, Wolf-Rayet 104,
是一颗大死星 濒临爆发成为一颗超新星
is a massive death star on the verge of exploding as a supernova.
那基本可以肯定的
That much is certain.
真正的奥秘在于
The real mystery is,
它是否会释放出伽玛射线暴(GRB)
will it also unleash a gamma ray burst, or GRB,
宇宙间最强的能量爆发呢？
the most powerful burst of energy in the universe?
问题在于事关整个地球
The question is an important one for all on Earth,
尤其要考虑该星轴可能正指向我们
especially considering the star's axis may be pointing directly at us.
那意味着一旦它爆发
That means that when it blows up,
如果它成为一个伽玛射线暴
if it becomes a gamma ray burst,
射流就会直接射向我们
the jet could be pointing straight at us.
WR104在人马座里倒数计时至毁灭
WR 104 is counting down to destruction in the constellation Sagittarius.
由罗马占星家在2000多年前命名
Named by Roman astrologers over 2,000 years ago,
人马座是拉丁语里的射手
Sagittarius is Latin for The Archer.
你必定会问
And you have to ask,
古人或许了解了什么
maybe were the ancients onto something?
射手瞄准我们是否与什么有关？
Is there something to do with The Archer aiming at us?
WR 104可以看作是一支箭指向我们
WR 104 can be thought of as an arrow pointing our way,
如果它确实爆发成为伽玛射线暴的话
if indeed it blows up as a gamma ray burst.
现在的天文学家已几乎没有争议
There is little dispute among today's astronomers
伽玛射线暴发出的集束射流
that a tightly focused beam from a gamma ray burst
会在太空中穿行遥远的距离
will travel vast distances in space.
事实上 在2009年4月23日
In fact, on April 23, 2009,
环绕地球的斯威夫特多波长观测站
the Swift multiwavelength observatory orbiting the Earth
记录到一个距离地球130亿光年的伽玛射线暴
recorded a GRB that occurred 13 billion light-years away from Earth,
几乎就在可见宇宙的边缘
near the very edge of the visible universe.
爆发就发生在大爆炸后6 5亿年前后
The blast occurred only about 630 million years after the Big Bang.
这意味着爆发恒星所发出的伽玛射线
This means that gamma rays from the exploding star
以光速穿行了130亿光年后
traveled at the speed of light for 13 billion years
才让我们看到
before they were visible to us,
使这个伽玛射线暴成为了
making this gamma ray burst
已知宇宙间最古老的星际物体
the oldest stellar object in the known universe.
我们知道没有恒星或星系
We know of no star or galaxy
有比这个伽玛射线暴更加遥远的
that's farther away than this gamma ray burst.
这是所见过的最遥远 最孤立的天体了
It's the single most distant, discrete object ever seen.
仅仅8000光年
At only 8,000 light-years,
沃尔夫-拉叶星104的伽玛射线暴可能是灾难性的
a GRB blast from Wolf-Rayet 104 could be catastrophic.
沃尔夫-拉叶星104爆发时 我们所看到的闪光
The flash that we would see if Wolf-Rayet 104 went off
会比太阳亮N多倍
would be much brighter than the Sun,
尤其是伽玛射线能量
especially at gamma ray energies.
单个伽玛射线暴可以轻而易举超过
A single gamma ray burst can easily exceed
数百万个星系所发出的总的光量
the total light output of millions of galaxies.
那些星系中每一个都含有上千亿颗恒星
And each of those galaxies contains a hundred billion stars.
这种死亡之星是滴答作响的定时炸弹
This death star is a ticking time bomb.
科学家知道它无疑会成为超新星的
Scientists know for sure it will go supernova.
但是问题就在于它有可能
But questions remain about its potential
释放的伽玛射线暴直接对准地球
to unleash a gamma ray burst in the direction of Earth.
首先我们需要进行确认
That's the first point we need to establish.
如果它会产生伽玛射线暴
If it does produce a gamma ray burst,
伽玛射线暴是否就指向我们呢？
is that gamma ray burst pointing towards us?
该星的旋转轴
The spiraling axis of the star
似乎对着地球的方向
appears to be aimed in the direction of Earth.
但是经过了数千光年的穿行
But with thousands of light-years to travel,
伽玛射线暴的射流会真的击中目标吗？
would the GRB beam actually hit the target?
射手之箭真是那回事吗？
Would The Archer's aim be true?
我们知道它大致指向我们
We know it's pointing roughly toward us,
但是它可指得够远的了
but it could be pointing sufficiently away
就是伽玛射线暴发出的辐射束
that the beam of radiation from the gamma ray burst,
没准它变成伽玛射线暴后
if it turns into a gamma ray burst,
实际上会和我们擦肩而过
will actually miss us.
不过 要是该星对准了 一个强大的能量爆发
However, if the star is aligned, one powerful burst of energy
可以将地球的臭氧层变成放射线的炼狱
could turn the Earth's ozone layer into a radioactive inferno.
即使是数千光年外的伽玛射线暴
Even a gamma ray burst that's thousands of light-years away
也会将臭氧层消耗到现有水平的一半
could deplete the ozone layer to roughly half of its current level.
此时 不会杀死所有的物种
Now, that won't kill all of the species,
但是却会导致我们所谓的大灭绝
but it could lead to what we call a mass extinction,
整个生物物种中有相当部分会突然死亡
where a good fraction of all living species die rather suddenly.
因此亟待解决的问题是 WR104的死亡
So the burning question is, will the death of WR 104
是否真的会引发伽玛射线暴呢？
really trigger a gamma ray burst?
科学家浑然不知
Scientists just don't know.
恒星引发致命的伽玛射线暴的必要条件
The mandatory requirement for a star to produce a lethal gamma ray burst
是高速旋转
is high-horsepower rotation.
所有的恒星都围绕着自己的轴旋转
All stars rotate on their axes.
有些大质量恒星可以飞快地旋转
Some massive stars can spin very fast.
因此旋转的恒星 转动能
So the rotating star, the rotational energy,
就是引发伽玛射线暴的一部分
is part of what produces the gamma ray burst.
如果你可以安装上制动器
If you could put the brakes on,
如果你可以在其到达那个阶段前
if you could take that rapidly spinning star
将那颗飞速旋转恒星的速度降下来
and slow it down before it gets to that stage,
你就拆除那颗炸弹了
you've defused that bomb.
基于越来越多的科学证据 似乎宇宙本身
Based on mounting scientific evidence, it appears the universe itself
也在对其恒星加上另一套制动器
is applying another set of brakes to its stars.
就是所谓的金属度
It's called metallicity.
恒星的主要成分是氢和氦
Stars are primarily made of hydrogen and helium,
但是更重 更复杂的元素诞生于每一次星体爆炸中
but heavier, more complex elements are created every time a star explodes,
元素有碳 氮 氧之类
elements like carbon, nitrogen, and oxygen,
会变成下一代恒星的原材料
that then become the raw materials for the next generation of stars.
因此现在诞生的恒星有较多的重元素
So a star born today has more heavy elements,
也就是所谓的高金属度
also known as a higher metallicity,
要高于宇宙历史上早期诞生的恒星
than a star born earlier in the history of the universe.
一旦大质量恒星含有大量的重元素
When a massive star has a lot of heavy elements in it,
往往会通过星风失去自身大量的质量
it tends to lose a lot of its mass through winds.
如果它失去自身大量的质量 也会降慢自己的旋转
And if it loses a lot of its mass, it also loses a lot of its rotation,
最终会慢到难以形成伽玛射线暴
and it ends up rotating too slowly to form a GRB.
因此说不定沃尔夫-拉叶星现在所发生的
So something is happening to the Wolf-Rayet stars today
就是走向那步 在拆除所有的炸弹
that's going up there and defusing all the bombs.
因而它们还会爆发成超新星
So they're still blowing up as supernovae,
但是其中极个别的
but far, far fewer of them
会把超新星推向下一步 成为伽玛射线暴
are taking that supernova to the next step as a gamma ray burst.
这些制动器会把WR104放慢到
Could these brakes slow WR 104 enough
使其对地球没有危害吗？
to render it harmless to the Earth?
许多天文学家对此深信不疑
Many astronomers believe so.
但要是他们错了呢？
But what if they're wrong?
相距8000光年 地球真的是在危险区了吗？
At 8,000 light-years away, is Earth really in the danger zone?
一旦叫做WR104的死亡之星最终爆发
When the death star called WR 104 finally explodes,
可能会引发致命的伽玛射线暴 直接对准地球
it has the potential to unleash a deadly gamma ray burst directly at Earth.
据信该星距离我们约8000光年
It's believed the star is roughly 8,000 light-years away from us.
这是否近得足以让伽玛射线暴
Is this close enough for a gamma ray burst
危及我们的星球呢？
to do damage to our planet?
介于5000到8000光年之间 那是个危险区
Being 5,000 to 8,000 light-years away, it's in the danger zone.
地球生命会在辐射抵达我们时 遭遇沉重打击
Earth's life might take a bad hit when that radiation reaches us.
如果距离远上两到三倍
lf it was another two or three times further away,
我们可能就没事了
we'd probably be okay.
如果它近上两到三倍
And if it was two or three times closer,
我们真的就两腿发抖了
we'd really be shaking in our boots.
不过要就在其范围的边缘
But it's just at the edge of its range
如人们所料 你知道 它可能会有所动作的
where one would expect, well, you know, it might do something,
但是也可能不会将我们所有人都烤至长眠不醒
but it's probably not going to roast us all in our sleep.
或许是每10亿年左右一回
So perhaps once every billion years or so,
伽玛射线暴相当靠近
there's a gamma ray burst that's sufficiently cIose
和相当瞄准我们 那是我们需要提防的
and sufficiently well-pointing toward us that we need to worry.
各种规模的死星生存在宇宙间
Death stars of all sizes populate the universe.
但是恒星并非唯一表现出如此暴力的物体
But stars are not the only entities capable of such violence.
宇宙还有3C321之类的死亡星系
The universe is also home to death galaxies like 3C321,
也叫做死星系
also known as the Death Star Galaxy.
3C321是个星系 其中央有一个巨大的黑洞
3C321 is a galaxy with a giant black hole in the middle,
其质量是我们太阳的数百万倍
millions of times the mass of our Sun.
就在黑洞边缘的外围
Just outside the black hole's edge,
混乱的磁场和引力的扰动
the chaotic churning of magnetic fields and gravitational pull
引发了高能粒子喷射
has ignited a high-energy particle jet.
这些喷射并不罕见
These jets are not uncommon,
但是这一个正在鞭挞它的近邻
but this one is delivering a beating to its nearest neighbor.
3C321的情况非常有趣
The case of 3C321 is very interesting,
因为其影响到的另一个星系
because there happens to be another galaxy
相距有2万光年
20,000 light-years away.
那个星系里的恒星正遭受
The stars in that galaxy are being blasted
来自这些射流中的高能粒子和辐射的轰击
by the energetic particles and radiation from one of these jets.
X射线天文学家丹 埃文斯一直在跟踪死星系
X-ray astronomer Dan Evans has been tracking the Death Star Galaxy
及其暴力行为
and its violent behavior
他的观察点是位于波士顿郊外的钱德拉X射线卫星控制中心
from the Chandra X-ray Satellite Control Center outside Boston.
我们看到了黑洞所干的种种怪事
So we see black holes do kind of strange things.
但是只有很小一部分会喷射出这些强烈的射流 粒子
But only a very small fraction emit these powerful jets, particles,
甚至有极个别的
and a fraction even smaller,
如星系3C321 死星系
such as the 3C321 galaxy, the Death Star Galaxy,
会猛击其伙伴星系
smack into other companion galaxies.
那是相当罕见的
So that's incredibly rare.
该伙伴星系隔着星际大街
The companion galaxy is across the galactic street,
相距2万光年
20,000 light-years distant.
强劲的能量射束
The massive energy beam,
甚至超过了死星发出的伽玛射线暴
even larger than a gamma ray burst from a dying star,
发射永不停歇 貌似其能量供应永无止境
is firing nonstop with a seemingly limitless energy supply.
我们现在所看到的就是对死星系3C321
So what we're looking at here is the best terrestrial analogy
最现实的比喻
for the Death Star Galaxy, 3C321.
射流冲出黑洞
A jet is racing out of the black hole,
接近光速 它实际上 -
close to the speed of light, and it's actually--
通常它会喷到百万光年以外
Normally it would propagate up to about a million light-years away,
但是在3C321的特殊案例里
but in the special case of 3C321,
射流猛击伙伴星系那一边
that jet is slamming into the side of a companion galaxy,
在这情况下 它就变得撕裂了
and in doing so, it's becoming disrupted
扭曲了 弯曲了
and distorted and bent away.
这给那颗伙伴星系施加了种种暴行
And that's wreaking all sorts of havoc to that companion galaxy.
就像建筑物偏转了水柱一般
Much like the building is deflecting the water jet,
受害星系里的行星和恒星
the planets and stars in the victimized galaxy
偏转了大部分攻击的粒子
are deflecting most of the attacking particles.
这条射流实际上是巨大的能量粒子束
So this jet is actually a massive beam of energy and particles.
这些粒子处于超高温状态
And these particles have been superheated
形成了等离子体
such that they form a plasma.
等离子体是超高温的带电粒子和离子的混合体
Plasma is a mix of super-hot charged electrons and ions
黑洞巨大的磁场将其注入射流中
funneled into the jet by the black hole's immense magnetic field.
因此冲出黑洞的射流
So jets that race out of black holes
实际上是极具能量的
are actually incredibly energetic,
事实上 它们可以加速粒子
and, in fact, they can accelerate particles
直到发出光 甚至伽玛射线
such that they emit light, maybe even up to gamma rays.
这些射线强劲得惊人
These rays are incredibly powerful.
并且相当持久
And very long-lasting.
有估计认为死星系喷发的能量束
Some estimates say the energy jet from the Death Star Galaxy
已经持续了近200万年了
has been firing for nearly two million years.
为了获得燃料 3C321简直生吞了整个星系
For its fuel, 3C321 simply devoured an entire galaxy.
它获得了大量的燃料
It's got a lot of fuel.
我们认为现在所发生的事情
What we actually think is happening here
就是先前曾有过兼并
is that there's been a previous merger,
因而另一个星系已经坠入了主星系
so another galaxy has fallen into the main galaxy.
我们来看这条漂亮的尘埃带
We see this beautiful dust lane,
那意味了那个星系已被撕碎
which implies that the galaxy's been shredded already.
结果撕扯行为将物质赶进了黑洞
And so that act of shredding drives mass down onto the black hole.
在耗尽另一个星系所提供的等离子粒子后
After consuming another galaxy's provision of plasma particles,
死星系得设法将粒子激发成射流
the Death Star Galaxy has to somehow energize the particles into a jet.
黑洞具有强大的磁场
Black holes have powerful magnetic fields
和超高速的旋转
and superfast spin rates,
两者结合怎么都得引发粒子射流
a combination that somehow ignites the particle jet.
科学家认为射流往一个方向发射的原因
Scientists believe the reason the jets fire in one direction
必定与所有的粒子气体围绕着黑洞运转有关
has to do with all the dust and gas circling the black hole.
在3C321这样的活跃星系的案例里
In the case of an active galaxy like 3C321,
其中心有一个超大质量黑洞
which has a supermassive black hole in the center,
你通常会看到一个面包圈 或环状 物质团团围住它
you'll often have a doughnut, or torus, of material surrounding it.
在此情况下 黑洞附近的高能粒子
In that case, highly energetic particles near the black hole
是无法从通过面包圈的地方
can't emerge from that region through the doughnut
沿着星系的平面喷出
along the plane of the galaxy.
它们只能顺着这个轴喷出
They can only emerge along this axis,
那里相对较少阻挡的物质
where there's relatively little obstructing material.
不行的是其伙伴星系
Unfortunately for the companion galaxy,
就眼睁睁地笔直地掉入了面包圈的洞里
it's staring straight down the doughnut hole,
射流的影响区
and the jet's zone of impact
宛如宇宙霰弹枪的爆炸扩散区
is like the widely scattered blast of a cosmic shotgun.
这种高速粒子辐射射流打击
The problem with this jet of high-speed particles and radiation
2万光年外的效星系所带来的问题
hitting the little galaxy 20,000 light-years away
是射流宽到足以
is that the jet is wide enough
覆盖该星系里大量的恒星
to encompass a large number of stars in this galaxy.
所以该星系里的围绕任何恒星的任何行星上的
So any creatures living on any planets
任何生物现在都险境重重了
orbiting any stars in that galaxy are in serious trouble right now.
要是我们的银河系
What if it were our own Milky Way
现在正遭死星系打击 又当如何呢？
being blasted by the Death Star Galaxy?
把地球置于射流的路径上
Put Earth in the path of the jet,
对臭氧层的影响将会是严重和致命的
and the effect on the ozone layer would be enormous and deadly.
3C321发出的射流里的伽玛射线
The gamma rays from the jet in 3C321
把氮转换成氮氧化物
convert nitrogen gas into nitrous oxides.
就是那些氮氧化物
And it's those nitrous oxides
充当了破坏臭氧的催化剂
that actually act as a catalyst in the destruction of ozone.
经过数周 数月
So within a matter of weeks to months,
乃至一年
maybe up to a year,
臭氧层就会被完全毁掉
the ozone layer will be completely obliterated.
那是个危险的后果
That's a nasty consequence.
但是和宇宙间所看到的许多现象一样
But like many phenomena observed in the universe,
存在着一个循环的悖论 - 有死才有生
there is a recurring paradox-- from death comes life.
3C321不仅在破坏 而且还在创造
3C321 not only destroys, it also creates.
我对3C321最感兴趣的地方
It's one of my favorite things about 3C321
就是它清楚地证明了
is it demonstrates really clearly
黑洞不只是吞噬着宇宙间的一切
that black holes don't just gobble everything up in the universe.
它们不全是毁灭的使者
They're not all complete harbingers of destruction.
从3C321射出的射流
The jet that is coming out in 3C321
击打着伙伴星系的这一面
is hammering into the side of the companion galaxy,
当然啦 那是破坏的力量
and, yes, of course, that's a destructive force,
但是最终的遗产
but the ultimate legacy
其实是在互动中被压缩的气体云
actually is that the gas clouds that get compressed during this interaction
实际上可以形成恒星 恒星又可以形成行星
can actually form stars, and the stars can form planets,
而行星就有可能形成生命
and the planets may even form life.
所以这种生死不息的美丽循环
So there's this beautiful cycle of birth and rebirth and destruction
就是宇宙和黑洞的代名词
that's synonymous with the universe and black holes.
未来有朝一日
One day in the future,
我们所处的银河系也可能与
our own Milky Way could form its own merger
邻近的仙女座星系合并成自己的联合体产生新的死星系
with the nearby Andromeda Galaxy and create a new Death Star Galaxy,
其暴行一定会给地球带来厄运
a violent act that would certainly spell doom for the Earth.
这样的事件很可能发生在未来的几十亿年里
Such an event would likely occur many billions of years in the future.
不过还有其它星际威胁
But there are other stellar threats
正以高速闯入我们的星系
streaking through our galaxy at high speed.
它们是超高速恒星 来势汹汹 势不可挡
They are hypervelocity stars, and nothing can stop them.
在人类眼里
To the human eye,
群星在苍穹描绘出一幅宁静的画面
stars paint a tranquil picture in the heavens above.
但是凑近一看
But take an up-close look.
其中有些是濒临毁灭的死星
A select few are death stars on the verge of extinction,
这些宇宙巨兽唯恐天下不乱
and these cosmic beasts are anything but peaceful.
恒星最终会烧尽其核心所有的氢
Eventually a star will burn through all the hydrogen in its core
全部转变成氦
and convert it all to helium.
一旦到那地步 它就必须质量大到足以
Once it does that, it has to be massive enough
能够点燃氦
to be able to ignite the helium
并将氦转换成重元素
and convert helium into heavier elements
如碳 氧 氮
like carbon, oxygen and nitrogen.
这会释放出巨大的能量
And this releases an enormous amount of energy.
这个过程也就是氢弹内部
This process is the same release of energy
所发生的能量释放
that goes on inside a hydrogen bomb.
尽管它们极其暴戾
Though they are incredibly violent,
但是其中多数星会有朝一日耗尽燃料
most of these stars will one day burn up
悄无声息进入后半生
and slip quietly into the afterlife
成为星际僵尸 即所谓的白矮星 -
as stellar corpses called white dwarf stars--
电子和原子构成的小球
smallish balls of electrons and nuclei,
注定不再会熊熊燃烧了
destined to never again burn brightly.
但有些是超大质量恒星
But some are supermassive stars,
精力充沛的它们会终结于惊天动地的超新星爆发中
so energetic they end in a fantastic supernova explosion,
有时甚至会产生最大的爆炸 -
and sometimes even produce the largest of all blasts,
伽玛射线暴
the gamma ray burst.
不过对于一些大质量死星来说 终结意味着新的开端
But for a few massive death stars, the end is a new beginning.
来看看中子星的第二次生命
Consider the second life of a neutron star.
大质量恒星爆发成为超新星时
When a massive star explodes in a supernova,
其星核有时会塌缩成一个黑洞
its core sometimes collapses to form a black hole.
但是更多的情形是
But much more frequently,
如果其核心的质量不够 不能形成黑洞
if the core isn't massive enough to create the black hole,
所形成的东西几乎一样怪异
it forms something almost as weird,
中子星 个头不大但密度难以置信
a neutron star, a small but incredibly dense body.
它实际上具有大量的物质
It actually has a huge amount of material
被压缩进了一个极小的空间
compressed into a very small space.
打个比方 你将我们整个太阳的质量
So you have, for example, the mass of our entire Sun
挤进只有几十英里的空间里
squeezed into a space maybe only a couple tens of miles across.
重力极强
The gravity is so strong
以至于恒星的原子里的质子和电子
that the protons and electrons inside the atoms of the star
实际上被挤在一起形成了中子
are actually pushed together to form neutrons.
中子星可以稳定存续数十亿年
And a neutron star can remain stable for billions of years.
中子星本身
Neutron stars by themselves
不会对宇宙邻居构成威胁
pose no danger to their celestial neighbors,
除非它们能找到搭档
unless they can find a partner.
你还能看到恒星的死亡场景
You can also get another death scenario for stars
两颗中子星之间好像有共同自杀的协定
where there's a sort of mutual suicide pact between two neutron stars.
它们叫做共轨中子星
These are called co-orbiting neutron stars,
其现象开始时 两颗中子星
a phenomenon initiated when two neutron stars
产生了一种亲密但注定一死的关系
begin an intimate, but doomed relationship.
它们的轨道在数十亿年后会收窄
Their orbit narrows over millions of years
直至它们最终相碰 化为一道闪光
until they finally meet in a flash of light.
在此过程中 它们会产生一个剧烈的爆发
And in so doing, they can generate a violent explosion,
某种意义上的第二次生命
a second life in a sense.
所以存在有两种不同的伽玛射线暴
So there's two different types of gamma ray bursts.
有短时间爆发
There's short bursts,
其持续时间不足2秒
which have durations of less than two seconds,
我们认为短时间爆发产生于
and we think that short bursts are produced
中子星的合并
by merging neutron stars.
短时间爆发不同于大质量恒星塌缩所产生的
The short bursts are different than the longer GRBs
时间较长的伽玛射线暴
produced by collapsing massive stars.
两颗碰撞的中子星所发出的伽玛射线暴
The gamma ray burst emitted by two colliding neutron stars
虽然时间短 但很强烈
may be short, but it's powerful,
等于太阳毕生发出的能量
equal to the energy released by the Sun
在2秒不到的时间里释放出来
over its entire lifetime in less than two seconds.
我们的担忧何在？
The worry for us?
至少有两打成双共轨的中子星
At least two dozen pairs of orbiting neutron stars
存在于银河系里
exist in the Milky Way.
很近的伽玛射线暴 首要的
A very nearby gamma ray burst, first and foremost,
会剥去大部分臭氧层
would get rid of much of the ozone layer.
那会给地球造成灾难性的后果
That could have disastrous effects on Earth.
有估计认为 暴虐的中子星合并
Some estimates hold that a violent neutron star merger
每一亿年会有一次发生在距太阳3000光年的范围内
occurs within about 3,000 light-years of the Sun every 100 million years.
这大概相当于地球化石记录所记载的
That's about the same interval as the mass extinction events
大规模灭绝事件的间隔时间
recorded in the Earth's fossil record.
那是巧合 还是我们应该担心
Is it coincidence, or should we worry
两颗垂死的恒星最后的探戈
that the last tango of two dying stars
有可能最终因为致命的伽玛射线轰击
might eventually blast the Earth's ozone layer
地球的臭氧层 进而改变地球呢？
with deadly gamma rays and alter the planet?
科学家无从回答
Scientists don't know the answer.
风险或许就如同
The chances are probably about the same
一颗速逃星冒失地闯入地球
as a runaway star plowing headlong into the Earth.
可能性极小
It's a remote possibility,
但不能掉以轻心
but fearsome to contemplate.
你实际上有可能看到群星簇拥
You can actually have the possibility that a collection of stars
或许都积聚在同一个街区里
that perhaps were all together in the same neighborhood,
彼此互动
interacting with each other,
有时会弹射出一颗恒星 离家游荡
sometimes ejects a star, just to wander off on its own.
据我们所知
As far as we know,
尚无游星奔我们而来
there are no wandering stars headed our way.
但要是发生那样的事情 将会是相当有趣的
But if that were to happen, it could be quite interesting.
可以看到的场景是围绕太阳的地球
One scenario could see the Earth's orbit around the Sun
将会受到游星引力的骚扰
disrupted by the gravitational pull of the wandering star.
一个戏剧性的后果就是这样一颗游星
One dramatic possibility is that such a wandering star
会将地球踹出整个太阳系
simply kicks the Earth entirely out of the solar system,
使得我们到处流浪
and so we're now wandering around
失去了能量的来源 - 太阳
without a source of energy, the Sun.
无人知道结局如何
No one really knows what would happen.
这取决于接近的角度
It really depends upon the angle of approach,
该星的质量 等等
the mass of the star, et cetera.
游星的速度可达到每秒60英里 -
Wandering stars can travel at up to 60 miles per second--
很快 但还是未达到快得足以
fast, but still not fast enough
摆脱银河系的引力
to escape the Milky Way's gravitational pull.
但是有一些涡轮增压型
But there are some supercharged turbo models
实际上可以挣脱逃逸 飞进宇宙间
that could actually break free and rocket out into the universe.
它们叫做超高速星
These are called hypervelocity stars.
超高速星是太阳一类的普通恒星
Hypervelocity stars are normal stars like the Sun,
除了它们跑出星系的速度
except that they're moving out of the galaxy
大大超过时速百万英里
at well over a million miles an hour.
那已经超越了银河系的逃逸速度
And that's beyond the escape velocity of the Milky Way.
需要有速度才能让一对普通的共轨恒星
The need for speed begins with a normal pair of co-orbiting stars
十分靠近黑洞的边缘
that get too close to the edge of a black hole.
就像发生故障的阿波罗13号指令舱
Just as the disabled Apollo 13 command module
通过机动接近月球的轨道来提升速度一样
got a boost to velocity by maneuvering close to the Moon's orbit,
超高速星从黑洞获得巨大的引力反冲
the hypervelocity star gets a huge gravitational kick from the black hole,
割断与其双胞胎伙伴的关系
severing the bond with its binary partner.
最靠近黑洞的恒星
The star closest to the black hole
会陷入围绕黑洞的贴身轨道
is captured into a very tight orbit
这样它就无能为力了
around the black hole, and so it loses this energy.
另一颗恒星就获得了能量
The other star gains that energy,
结果就以这种极大的速度被弹射出来了
and is ejected with this very large velocity as a result.
超高速星的射出很像是弹弓效应
The ejection of a hypervelocity star is much like a slingshot effect.
瞬间双星的轨道被打破
At the instant the binary star's orbit is broken,
超高速星以极大的力道被射入浩瀚的空间
the hypervelocity star is launched with incredibIe force into the void of space.
它们一经被逐出银河系
They've been voted out of the Milky Way,
就注定漂泊在无边无际的太空之中
and they're destined to drift into the empty depths of intergalactic space.
这些恒星影响到地球是非常不可能的
It's very unlikely that these stars will ever affect the Earth.
幸运的是 这些超高速星的老死
Fortunately, the eventual death of these speedy stars
会发生在离太阳很远很远的地方
will occur far away from our solar system.
那些在我们街区里的死星才是我们需要警惕的
It's the death stars on our own block we need to keep an eye on.
在宇宙时间里 它们的引信已经点绕
In cosmic time, their fuses are lit,
我们首当其冲它们的湮灭
and we have a front-row seat to their annihilation.
在宇宙偏远的角落里
In remote corners of the universe,
无数恒星正在死囚牢房里等待着
countless stars are biding their time on death row,
被处以壮丽暴虐的极刑
sentenced to spectacular, violent endings.
离家不远处 有几十颗恒星
Closer to home, there are a few dozen stars
就在距地球20光年的范围内
within 20 light-years of the Earth.
其中有些正在准备后事
And a few of these are preparing for death.
我认为我们对普通超新星的威胁是安全的
I think we're safe from the dangers of a normal supernova.
对于伽玛射线暴的情况 我们不敢打包票
In the case of a gamma ray burst, we're not so sure.
其中有在船底座伊塔星系里
One is in the stellar system Eta Carinae,
一颗超新星比我们太阳大100倍
a supermassive star about 100 times bigger
亮100万倍
and a million times more luminous than the Sun.
1843年 积聚的压力
In 1843, a buildup of pressure
点燃的巨大的光喷发 在地球上都能看到
ignited a gigantic eruption of light seen from Earth.
但是该星存活了下来
But the star survived
形成了尘埃云 叫做星云
and formed a dust cloud called a nebula.
就在8000光年以外
At a distance of just 8,000 light-years,
我们首当其冲它的毁灭
we'll have a front-row seat to its annihilation.
我们认为它会变成黑洞
We think it's going to turn into a black hole
就在现在到未来的100万年里的某个时间
sometime between now and the next million years,
随着它的塌缩 它有足够的物质
and as it collapses, it has enough matter
它可以产生强烈的伽玛射线暴
that it can produce a powerful gamma ray burst.
不像沃尔夫-拉叶星104
Unlike the star Wolf-Rayet 104,
船底座伊塔星并没有把我们纳入它的准星
Eta Carinae doesn't have us in its crosshairs.
我们知道船底座伊塔的旋转
We know that the rotation of Eta Carinae
并没有正对地球
is not pointed towards Earth.
所以我们很幸运 伽玛射线柱
So lucky for us, the pulse of the gamma ray
并不会直接影响到地球
is not going to be directly impacting Earth.
如果那样
When it happens,
爆发有可能会是人类所见证到的最亮的超新星
the explosion will likely be the brightest supernova ever witnessed by mankind
除非冠军旁落另一颗死星竞争者
unless the title goes to another death star contender
就是更加靠近地球的
that's even closer to Earth--
参宿四
Betelgeuse.
位于500光年外的猎户座里
Located in the Orion constellation about 500 light-years away,
参宿四正快速耗尽其最后的核燃料
Betelgeuse is quickly burning through the last of its nuclear fuel.
参宿四是颗很大的恒星 其质量是太阳的20倍
Betelgeuse is a very massive star, about 20 times the mass of the Sun.
会在50万年里爆发
And it's within half a million years of exploding.
人们关注到参宿四
People have been noticing that Betelgeuse
在过去的数十年里变化很大
has been changing a lot over the last decades.
它实际上大幅收缩 约有15%
It's actually shrunk considerably, about 15%.
意味着什么 无人知晓
What that means, no one is sure,
但是大家都不敢掉以轻心
but everyone's keeping an eye on it.
有些科学家认为参宿四可能会释放出伽玛射线暴
Some scientists believe Betelgeuse could unleash a gamma ray burst.
地球人对此无庸担忧
People on Earth have little to fear if it does.
和船底座伊塔星一样 其星轴指向安全地远离地球
Like Eta Carinae, the star's axis points safely away from Earth.
不仅如此 而且参宿四还可能具有
Not only that, but Betelgeuse may also have
内置的爆炸屏障
a built-in blast shield.
其爆发会相对平常
Its explosion will be relatively normal.
它不会是伽玛射线暴
It won't be a gamma ray burst,
因为参宿四存在着厚厚的氢气外壳
because there's this thick hydrogen envelope in Betelgeuse,
氢气外壳
and that hydrogen envelope
可能会阻挡住喷射中的粒子辐射流
will probably prevent the jet of particles and radiation from emerging.
辐射流里会有大量的物质送出
There's too much material through which the jet of radiation would have to pass.
参宿四会短时间内强烈发光
Betelgeuse will shine intensely for a brief moment,
但是比不上我们最近的恒星 - 太阳的最后时刻
but it won't compare to the final moments of our nearest star, the Sun.
我们太阳这样的普通恒星 健康长寿
Average stars like our Sun have nice, long life spans,
我们幸运的是
fortunately for us,
我们的太阳才度过了它百亿年寿命的一半
and our Sun is about halfway through its 10-billion-year lifetime.
它才45亿岁左右
So it's about 4 1/2 billion years old.
步入中年
That makes it middle-aged.
科学家估计太阳还能活50亿年
Scientists estimate that the Sun will live another 5 billion years,
但是我们的问题会更早产生
but our problems could begin much sooner.
我们的太阳在逐步变得明亮
Our own Sun is very gradually getting brighter,
变得更加强劲
getting more powerful.
在50亿年 肯定是100亿年里
And within a half a billion, certainly a billion years,
地球将会变得非常的热
the Earth will become so hot
海洋将会蒸发殆尽
that the oceans will have evaporated away.
因此我们是不会有四五十亿年
So we don't quite have 4 or 5 billion years
来操心这个问题了
to worry about this problem.
我们必须要对此操心的时间尺度就几亿年的时间
We have to worry about it on time scales of hundreds of millions of years.
在太阳让地球聊无生机的几十亿年后
Billions of years after the Sun renders the Earth devoid of life,
就会进入最后阶段 所谓的红巨星时代
it will enter a final phase, known as a red giant.
它不可能爆发成为超新星的
It can't explode and produce a supernova,
因为它个头不够
because it's not massive enough.
但是大多数科学家都赞同最后的篇章
But most scientists agree on the final chapter.
作为红巨星 其密度会减小
As a red giant, its density will decrease,
太阳会向外膨胀 吞噬它的近邻
and the Sun will balloon outward, devouring its nearest neighbors.
在此阶段 红巨星阶段
At this stage, the red giant stage,
太阳会膨胀 吞噬水星 金星
the Sun will probably expand and engulf Mercury, Venus,
或许还有地球本身
and maybe even Earth itself.
因此 那几乎是地球的末日
So that would pretty much be the end of Earth.
在宇宙间所有的死星威胁中
Of all the dangerous death stars in the universe,
最有可能摧毁地球的就是我们的太阳
the one most likely to destroy the Earth is our own Sun.
虽然这标志着我们星球的终结
While it marks our planet's ultimate end,
但它只不过是宇宙循环的一部分
it's merely a part of the cycle of creation.
死星杀生 但是它们也是生命的起源
Death stars take life, but they are also the origin of life.
我们体内的重元素
The heavy elements in our bodies
毫不夸张地说是产生于前几代的恒星
quite literally were generated by previous generations of stars
是自星际爆发中射入宇宙的
and ejected into the cosmos by stellar explosions.
因此如果不是发生了某些恒星在其生命结束时
So we would not be here if it were not for the fact that some stars
剧烈的爆发的话 我们就不会在这里了
explode violently at the end of their lives.
正如卡尔 萨根说过的那样
As Carl Sagan used to say,
我们是星际物质组成的 我们是星尘组成的
"We are made of star stuff, we are made of stardust."
随着爆发的不断进行 产生出重元素
As the explosions continue, the resulting heavy elements
或许有朝一日再次播下生命的基础
may one day re-seed the very foundations of life,
远离银河
far from the Milky Way,
在宇宙新的一角的一颗新的蓝色星球上
on a new blue planet